Finding Aid for Vice Provost for Academic and Multicultural Affairs (University of Michigan) records, 1970-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Vice Provost for Academic and Multicultural Affairs (University of Michigan) records
1970-2000
1987-1998
University of Michigan. Vice Provost for Academic and Multicultural Affairs.
93852 Bimu 2
The office of the Vice Provost for Academic and Multicultural Affairs was originally established to develop and support programs to aid the University of Michigan in the recruitment and retention of students, faculty, and staff of color. The scope of the duties of the office were later expanded to include administrative oversight of a number of programs and services for faculty and students. The bulk of the record group is comprised of topical files related to multicultural issues, correspondence and reports relating to particular initiatives and funding programs, and administrative office files.
42 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the offices of the Vice Provost for Minority Affairs and the Vice Provost for Academic and Multicultural Affairs (donor no. 8046 ) in a series of accessions beginning in 1993.
The records of the Vice Provost for Academic and Multicultural Affairs are open for research with the exception of certain types of files restricted in accord with applicable law and university policy. This record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Box 12, 41-42
Student Academic Records -- Box 12, 41-42
Client/Patient Records -- Boxes 41-42
Executive Officers Records -- Boxes 30-40
In June 1987, Charles D. Moody, Sr., was appointed the university’s first Vice Provost for Minority Affairs (VPMA). Dr. Moody, a professor of education and director of the Program for Educational Opportunity in the School of Education since 1970, had long been active in the area of minority issues, especially education for underprivileged youths. As VPMA, he was given the responsibility for developing programs to aid the University of Michigan in the recruitment and retention of minority students, faculty, and staff, and for creating and staffing an Office of Minority Affairs to assist in these goals.
Previously these duties had been the responsibility of the associate vice president for academic affairs. This position had been vacant since Niara Sudarkasa’s departure in January 1987 to become president of Lincoln University in Pennsylvania. The impetus for the elevation of this position to the executive level and the addition of an Office of Minority Affairs is found in the campus events of February and March 1987.
In February 1987, a group of students, concerned with the increasing number of acts of racism occurring on campus and frustrated at the apparent lack of action by the administration, formed the United Coalition Against Racism (UCAR). UCAR developed a list of twelve demands designed to provide long-term, institutional mechanisms to combat racism at the university, one of which was the establishment of an Office of Minority Affairs with an autonomous supervisory commission elected by the minority campus community. These demands were presented to President Shapiro on March 5, 1987, following a march to the Fleming Building. At this time, students stated that, unless the demands were met, it would be necessary to organize a third Black Action Movement (BAM III). Previous Black Action Movements, BAM I and BAM II, had taken place in 1970 and 1975; BAM I succeeded in crippling the university for thirteen days through boycotts of classes and work.
BAM III was launched on March 18, 1987, with a march by over 350 students to the Diag, a rally, and a boycott of the Michigan Union. Also, BAM III presented a list of eleven demands to the administration, which incorporated the demands developed by UCAR. On March 20, members of UCAR, protesting the lack of action on their demands, staged a sit-in at the Fleming Building. Aware that Rev. Jesse Jackson was visiting the Detroit area, BAM III invited him to speak to the students and assist them in their efforts. After 24 hours of negotiations with Jackson acting as mediator, student representatives, President Shapiro, and university administrators announced a Six-Point Plan of Action. One of the points stated that the position of associate vice president for academic affairs would be elevated to the vice provost level with responsibility for an Office of Minority Affairs.
Dr. Moody was the vice provost for minority affairs from his appointment in 1987 until June 1993, when he was appointed executive director of the university’s South Africa Initiative Office. His successor, Lester Monts, assumed the position with the new title of Vice Provost for Academic and Multicultural Affairs (VPAMA). This title reflected the expansion of the responsibilities of the position, including administrative oversight of the Center for Research on Learning and Teaching and the Reserve Officer Training Corps, as well as oversight of the Office of Academic Multicultural Initiatives (the new name for the Office of Minority Affairs). When the Office of New Student Programs was created in 1995, it also reported to the vice provost for academic and multicultural affairs.
In 1997 Dr. Monts' title was changed to Associate Provost for Academic and Multicultural Affairs; again his office took on additional responsibilities, including oversight of the offices of Undergraduate Admissions, Financial Aid and the Registrar. Monts’ title was changed again in January 2001 to Senior Vice Provost for Academic and Multicultural Affairs.
(The events on campus leading up to the creation of the Office of Minority Affairs and the Vice Provost for Minority Affairs position are well documented in February and March 1987 issues of the student newspaper The Michigan Daily, and in the six Special Editions of The University Record, the newspaper for faculty and staff, published in March and April 1987.)
The records of the Vice Provost for Academic and Multicultural Affairs document the activities and functions of the office from its creation in 1987 through 2000. The record group has been received in increments over the years, with some overlap in content between different accessions; the researcher may want to consult the files in multiple accessions to ensure receiving the most complete account of a particular subject. Some scattered records predating the formal establishment of the office are present in the early accessions. The record group consists of records of Vice Provost Charles D. Moody, Sr. and Lester Monts relating to work of the Office; series concern relations of office with outside organizations as well as activities within the university. It also includes administrative files, chronological files, and files on units reporting to the Office such as Military Officer Education Programs and Undergraduate Admissions.
While the earlier accessions mainly concern the vice provost’s involvement in multicultural affairs, later accessions include information on the office’s broader academic affairs responsibilities, including administrative oversight of various student academic services. It should be noted that, for the most part, folder headings assigned by the vice provost’s office have been retained, and reflect the use of terms such as “African Americans,” “Blacks,” “Hispanics,” and “Latinos” by the office.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; Detroit (Mich.)--Social conditions.; Racism--Michigan.; Schools--Michigan--Detroit.; University of Michigan. Office of Minority Affairs.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.; University of Michigan. Vice Provost for Minority Affairs.; Minority college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Office of Academic Multicultural Initiatives.; University of Michigan. Vice Provost for Academic and Multicultural Affairs.; Multiculturalism--Michigan.; United States. Army. Reserve Officers' Training Corps.; Multicultural education.
Contributors:
Moody, Charles D.; Monts, Lester Parker.
- General Files
  - External Relations Topical Files, 1984-1992
    - African American Organizations and Events
      - General, 1986-1991 (Box 1)
      - Black History Month, 1985-1990 (Box 1)
      - Black Issues in Higher Education (BIHE)
        - General, 1990 (Box 1)
        - Teleconferences
          - General, 1989 (Box 1)
          - "Beyond the Dream: A Celebration of Black History,", 1989 (Box 1)
          - "The Black Athlete: Winners or Losers in Academia?,", 1990 (Box 1)
          - "Faculty Rights--Tenure and Governance: Negotiation vs. Litigation,", 1989 (Box 1)
          - "Men of Color: Absence in Academia,", 1990 (Box 1)
          - "Racism on Campus,", 1988 (Box 1)
          - "The State of Black Health Care,", 1989 (Box 1)
      - Black United Fund of Michigan, Inc., 1990 (Box 1)
      - Education of Black Youth, Select Committee on the, 1986 (Box 1)
      - Michigan Legislative Black Caucus, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
      - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP)
        - General, 1987; 1989 (Box 1)
        - Ann Arbor Chapter, 1987; 1989 (Box 1)
        - Detroit Chapter, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
        - Michigan State Conference of NAACP Branches, 1984-1989 (Box 1)
        - Ypsilanti Chapter, 1988-1991 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Police Department, 1989-1992 (Box 1)
    - Articles and Clippings (re: minority issues), 1988-1991; 4 folders (Box 1)
    - The Black Collegian magazine, 1988 (Box 1)
      (includes "Going Places" program)
    - The Black Student's Guide to Colleges, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Colleges and Universities (correspondence with), 1987-1991 (Box 1)
    - Committees, Councils, and Consortia
      - American Council on Education, 1988; 1991 (Box 1)
      - Michigan Minority Business Development Council, 1988-1991 (Box 1)
      - Minority Doctorates in Science, Consortium of Corporations and Universities to Increase (MINDS), 1989 (Box 1)
      - Minority Technology Council of Michigan, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
      - Think Tank Committee on the State of Black Michigan, Ad Hoc, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Community Colleges, 1989; 1991 (Box 1)
    - Conferences
      (includes presentations)
      - General, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
      - American Association of Higher Education, 1990 (Box 1)
      - American College Personnel Association, 1988 (Box 1)
      - Association of Black Administrators, 1984 (Box 1)
      - National Association For Equal Opportunity in Higher Education (NAFEO), 1988-1991 (Box 1)
      - National Black Graduate Student Conference, 1989-1991 (Box 1)
      - National Education Association, 1986-1990 (Box 1)
    - Consultants, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
      (includes their proposals)
    - Diversity (articles and clippings), 1987-1991 (Box 1)
    - Domino's Pizza, Inc., 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Donor Relations, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
    - Foundations
      - General, 1984-1991 (Box 1)
      - Ford Foundation, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
      - National Science Foundation, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
      - Spencer Foundation, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - Hispanic Organizations and Events
      - General, 1987-1991 (Box 2)
      - Consortium to Identify and Promote Hispanic Professionals, 1988-1993; 2 folders (Box 2)
        (includes material re: Hispanic Expert Resource Database)
      - Council of Hispanics for Higher Education (CHHE), 1987 (Box 2)
      - Michigan Coalition of Concerned Hispanics, Hispanic Leadership Conferences, 1988-1990 (Box 2)
      - Midwest Consortium for Latino Research, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs)
      - General, 1984-1992 (Box 2)
      - Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HCBU) and Hispanic Serving Institutions (HSI) Committee, 1987-1992 (Box 2)
      - HBCU Exchange Programs, 1987-1990 (Box 2)
    - Mandela, Nelson, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - Michigan, State of
      - General, 1987-1990 (Box 2)
      - Civil Rights, Department of, 1988-1991 (Box 2)
      - Education, Department of
        - General, 1988-1991 (Box 2)
        - Office of Minority Equity, 1987-1991 (Box 2)
      - Public Health, Department of, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Organizations and Associations
      - From Bars to Stars, 1987-1990 (Box 2)
      - National Urban Education Association, 1988 (Box 2)
      - Push For Excellence, Inc. (PUSH EXCEL), 1986-1989 (Box 2)
    - Persian Gulf War, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Public Schools
      - General, 1987-1990 (Box 2)
      - All Male Academy, 1991 (Box 2)
      - Ann Arbor Public Schools, 1985-1992 (Box 2)
      - Detroit Public Schools
        - General, 1984-1992; 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Detroit Board of Education, 1987-1991 (Box 2)
        - Detroit Compact
          - General, 1987-1992 (Box 2)
          - Agreements and Reports, 1988-1989; 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Detroit Public Schools and UM Collaborations
          - General, 1984-1991 (Box 2)
          - Collaboration Committee, 1985-1991 (Box 3)
          - Think Tank Session, May 1989 (Box 3)
        - Superintendent
          - General, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
          - Search, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
        - Urban Education Expert Panel, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
        - Wade McCree Incentive Scholarship Program
          - General, 1987-1992; 2 folders (Box 3)
          - Advisory Board, 1987-1991; 2 folders (Box 3)
          - Articles and Clippings, 1987-1990 (Box 3)
          - Budget and Funding, 1989-1991 (Box 3)
          - Housing, 1990 (Box 3)
          - Summer Initiative, 1989-1992 (Box 3)
      - Mackenzie High School, 1987-1991; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Superintendents, Black, 1985-1991 (Box 3)
      - Superintendents' Forum
        - 1988-1990, 3 folders (Box 3)
        - 1992 (Box 3)
      - Test-Wiseness Training Workshop, 1986; 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - Racism
      - Articles and Clippings, 1987-1990 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence from Concerned Citizens, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
    - Standardized Testing, 1988; 1990 (Box 3)
    - United States Government
      - Education, Department of, 1988-1991 (Box 3)
      - Energy, Department of, 1988 (Box 3)
      - Justice, Department of, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
      - Labor, Department of, 1988-1991 (Box 3)
      - Senate, 1987-1990 (Box 3)
    - Urban Leagues, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Files
    - Admissions
      - General, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
      - Complaints, 1988-1991 (Box 12)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2066 ]
      - Statistics 1988-1991 (includes statistics from 1983-1991) (Box 4)
      - Director of Admissions, Office of
        - General, 1987-1990 (Box 4)
        - Director Search, 1988 (Box 12)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2018 ]
      - Undergraduate Admissions, Office of, 1988-1991 (Box 4)
    - Affirmative Action
      - Affirmative Action Coordinators, 1987-1990 (Box 4)
      - Affirmative Action Office
        - General, 1985-1991 (Box 4)
        - Associate Director Search, 1987 (Box 12)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2017 ]
        - Director Search, 1989 (Box 12)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2019 ]
      - Articles and Clippings, 1988-1990 (Box 4)
    - African American Organizations and Events
      - General, 1987-1991 (Box 4)
      - Black Action Movement (BAM)
        - General, 1970-1988 (Box 4)
        - Articles and Clippings, 1987-1991 (Box 4)
        - Conference, 1989-1991 (Box 4)
    - African American Organizations and Events (cont.)
      - Black Professionals and Administrators at UM, Association of (ABPA), 1984-1991 (Box 4)
      - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), UM Chapter, 1985-1991 (Box 4)
    - Alumni Association
      - General, 1985-1991 (Box 4)
      - Annual All-Class Reunion for Black Graduates, 1987-1992 (Box 4)
      - Black Leadership Council, 1987-1988 (Box 4)
      - Minority Recruitment Programs, 1987-1991 (Box 4)
    - Centers and Institutes
      - Afro-American and African Studies, Center for (CAAS)
        - General, 1987-1991; 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Personnel, 1988-1991 (Box 12)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2021 ]
      - Ella Baker-Nelson Mandela Center for Anti-Racist Education, 1987-1991 (Box 4)
      - Gerontology, Institute of, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
      - Humanities, Institute for the, 1987-1988 (Box 4)
      - Medical Center
        - General, 1987-1991 (Box 4)
        - Personnel, 1987-1990 (Box 12)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2020 ]
      - Population Studies Center, 1987-1989 (Box 4)
      - Public Policy Studies, Institute of
        - General, 1988-1991 (Box 4)
        - Student, 1991 (Box 12)
      - Science and Technology, Institute of, 1987-1988 (Box 4)
      - Social Research, Institute for, 1988-1991 (Box 4)
    - Committees
      - Academic Affairs Advisory Council (AAAC)
        - General, 1989-1991 (Box 4)
        - Academic Affairs Advisory Council/ Executive Officers Diversity Retreats, 1987-1988; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Academic Services Board, 1987-1989 (Box 4)
      - Compensation Program Task Force (Task Force #5), undated (Box 4)
      - Diversity Commitment Task Force, 1987 (Box 4)
      - Grievance Review Committee, 1989; 1991 (Box 4)
      - Minority Concerns, Committee on, undated (Box 4)
      - Minority Student Recruitment Initiative in Health and Biological Sciences Task Force, 1986-1988 (Box 4)
      - Multicultural University, Council on a, 1991-1993 (Box 4)
      - President's Cabinet, 1989 (Box 5)
      - Provost's Administrative Group, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
      - Rainbow Think Tank, 1989 (Box 5)
      - Recruitment, Graduation, and Success of Students of Color, Provost's Commission on, 1990-1993; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SACUA), 1987-1991 (Box 5)
      - Undergraduate Admissions Advisory Committee, 1987; 1990 (Box 5)
      - Undergraduate Affairs, Council on, 1989-1991 (Box 5)
      - Women of Color Task Force, 1987-1991 (Box 5)
    - Diversity
      - Diversity Agenda, 1987-1990 (Box 5)
      - Workshops and Programs
        - General, 1987-1991 (Box 5)
        - Efficacy Program, 1988 (Box 5)
    - Employees
      - General, 1987-1991 (Box 5)
      - Restricted, 1987-1991 (Box 12)
    - Enrollment
      - General, 1986-1990 (Box 5)
      - Statistics, 1986-1991; 3 folders (Box 5)
        (includes stats from 1975-1991)
    - Executive Offices and Officers
      - General, 1986-1990 (Box 5)
      - Academic Affairs, Office of the Provost and Vice-President for
        - General, 1987-1991 (Box 5)
        - Assistant to Associate Vice President Search, 1986 (Box 12)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2016 ]
      - Development, Office of the Vice-President for, 1987-1991 (Box 5)
      - Government Relations, Office of the Vice-President for, 1987-1989 (Box 5)
      - President, Office of the, 1987-1990 (Box 5)
      - Research, Office of the Vice-President for
        - General, 1987-1990 (Box 5)
        - Diversity, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
      - Student Services, Office of the Vice-President for, 1987-1991 (Box 5)
    - Faculty, Minority
      - General
        - 1987-1991, 1 folders (Box 6)
        - 1987-1991, 1 folders (Box 12)
    - Faculty, Minority (cont.)
      - Allen, Walter
        - 1981-1991, 1 folders (Box 6)
        - 1981-1991, 1 folders (Box 12)
      - Bryant, Bunyan, 1989; 1991 (Box 6)
      - Dawson, Michael C., 1987-1988 (Box 6)
      - Deskins, Donald, 1987-1989 (Box 6)
      - Johnson, Ernest, 1988 (Box 6)
      - Morris, Aldon, 1987 (Box 12)
      - Ngate, Jonathan, 1983; 1987 (Box 12)
      - Recruitment and Retention, 1984-1988 (Box 6)
      - Statistics, 1989-1991; 2 folders (Box 6)
        (includes stats from 1977-1991)
      - Wilson, Ernie and Francille, 1987; 1990 (Box 12)
    - Financial Aid, 1985-1991; 2 folders (Box 12)
      [1 folder PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2021 ]
    - Graduation, 1988-1989 (Box 6)
      (includes statistics from 1977-1989)
    - Harassment Policy, 1989 (Box 6)
    - Hispanics
      - General, 1987-1991 (Box 6)
      - Hispanic Alumni Council, 1987-1991 (Box 6)
      - Hispanic Heritage Celebrations, 1987-1991 (Box 6)
      - Latino Resource Center, proposal, 1989 (Box 6)
      - Latino Studies Program
        - 1987-1991, 1 folders (Box 6)
        - 1987-1991, 1 folders (Box 12)
      - Students
        - "Latinos at Michigan: An Exploratory Study", 1990 (Box 6)
        - Recruitment, 1987-1991 (Box 6)
    - Holocaust, Conferences and Memorials, 1987-1990 (Box 6)
    - Housing, 1987-1991 (Box 6)
    - King/Chavez/Parks Educational Initiative
      - General, 1986-1991 (Box 6)
      - Budget, 1988-1991 (Box 6)
      - Committees
        - Advisory Committee, 1989-1990 (Box 6)
        - Coordinating Committee, 1987-1991 (Box 6)
      - Programs
        - College Day Program
          - General, 1988-1991 (Box 6)
          - College Club Program, 1988-1991 (Box 6)
          - Report, 1988/89 (Box 6)
          - Spring Visitations, 1988-1991 (Box 6)
          - Student Leadership Development Program
            - General
              - 1988-1990, 1 folders (Box 7)
              - 1988-1990, 1 folders (Box 12)
            - Evaluations
              - 1989, 1 folders (Box 7)
              - 1989, 1 folders (Box 12)
          - Summer Institutes, 1988-1990 (Box 7)
        - Fellowship Program
          - 1987-1990, 1 folders (Box 7)
          - 1987-1990, 1 folders (Box 12)
            [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2065 ]
        - Visiting Professorship Program
          - General, 1987-1991; 2 folders (Box 7)
          - Nominations, 1988-1991 (Box 7)
    - Libraries, 1987-1991 (Box 7)
    - Major Events, Office of, 1987-1991 (Box 7)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. Symposia
      - 1986-1987 (Box 7)
      - 1988 (Box 7)
        (includes memorial concert)
      - 1989-1991, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - 1992
        - General (Box 7)
        - Coordinator's Final Report (Box 7)
    - Michigan Mandate and Michigan Plan, 1988-1992 (Box 7)
    - Museums, 1987-1990 (Box 7)
    - Native Americans, 1987-1991 (Box 7)
    - News and Information Services, 1987-1988 (Box 7)
    - Orientation, Students
      - General, 1987-1990 (Box 7)
      - Minority Student Spring Visitation, 1988-1990 (Box 7)
      - Minority Student Welcome, 1985-1990 (Box 7)
      - Orientation Task Force, 1987-1988 (Box 7)
      - "Talk to Us" Program, 1988 (Box 7)
      - Video, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Physical Education, Division of (Box 8)
      - 1987-1989, 1 folders (Box 8)
      - 1987-1989, 1 folders (Box 8)
      - 1987-1989, 1 folders (Box 12)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2063 ]
    - Presidential Initiative Fund, 1991 (Box 8)
    - Programs
      - African Americans for Academic Achievement (4.A), 1990 (Box 8)
      - Bush Program in Child Development and Social Policy, 1987 (Box 8)
      - Comprehensive Studies Program (Box 8)
      - 1987-1991, 1 folders (Box 8)
      - 1987-1991, 1 folders (Box 12)
      - Conflict Management Alternatives, Program on, 1987 (Box 8)
      - Detroit Area Study Program
        - General, 1987-1989 (Box 8)
        - Allen Park Incident, 1989 (Box 8)
        - Conference, 1989 (Box 8)
      - Honors Program, 1988 (Box 8)
      - Intergroup Relations and Conflict, Program on, 1990 (Box 8)
      - Mentorship Program, 1991 (Box 8)
      - Scholarly Research for Urban/Minority High School Students, Program in, 1989-1991 (Box 8)
      - Women's Studies Program, 1989-1990 (Box 8)
    - Publications (correspondence with or about)
      - General, 1988-1991 (Box 8)
      - The Michigan Daily, 1988; 1990 (Box 8)
      - The Research News, 1987-1988 (Box 8)
    - Racism
      - General, 1987-1991 (Box 8)
      - Articles and Clippings, 1987-1991 (Box 8)
      - Courses, Workshops, and Programs, 1987-1990 (Box 8)
      - Incidents of Racism
        - General
          - 1987-1991, 1 folders (Box 8)